Hello, everyone, and welcome
to our first series of
lecture in your second year.
My name is Bardiya Askeri.
Some of you may have
remembered me from the one solo
lecture I gave you in
Foundations. And this, in a way,
is a continuation from that
lecture. So if you don't
remember the lecture, I
suggest that you kind of go
take a look at it either
after you do this to kind of
familiarize yourself with
some of the additional
concepts, but we will go through
some of the touch on some
of the things that we talked
about in that lecture.
The title of our lecture
is the physiology
of the solute transport
and fluid, fluid
movements through
biological barriers.
And it sets up the next
lectures on renal physiology,
or this is my belief, it
helps you understand the
functionality and the roles.
And it, and this lecture
will introduce you to some
of the language that we use
interchangeably in in the
next series of lectures.
So these are our session
objectives. They're
broken down in our CPG,
but you can also read here.
So five objectives,
a lot of definition,
identifying the structural
differences to different
capillaries is the only part that
may be a little bit different
and applying the principles
that we know about the
physiological forces responsible
for water and solute
movements across barriers.
So like that lecture,
let's start off with the
scenario. So, you know,
you've all come off your
first year. This is the
last time you're going have
a summer vacation so you
want to get back into
shape and you know you
ate a lot of junk food and
you won't you know you kind
of like didn't like the
way that you physically
looked at the end of uh
may so you decide to
exercise you have a friend
um that who's also a uh
does hot yoga and they talk
you into going you know
jogging to the hot yoga
studio um and uh going
through one session so
when you leave the studio
you just kind of like
after sweating you know
if you've ever been to hot
yoga you know that you
sweat from every possible
sweat gland in your body
and when you come out you
leave the studio, you
realize that, geez,
everything just feels
looser. You're tightening
your belt. And then you look
at your arms and you see
like, geez, everything is
so prominent. The veins
and everything are sticking
out and you are parched.
So what just happened to
me? I was feeling okay two
hours ago and what is going
on in my body and how can I
explain it to somebody
who's not very very familiar
and what else is going
on that you don't know.
So hopefully this
next bunch of slides
can help you
differentiate some of the
phenomena that happens
in these contexts.
So vigorous exercise,
excessive sweating, and
what has it got to do
with prominent vasculature
and weight loss?
You may remember this
slide. It's a breakdown of
our fluid compartments
in what's considered
to be an idealized
person, which I'd like
to tell you that it's
really not that ideal.
You know, when I was
in school, this 72, you
know, mythical 72 kilogram
person was considered to
be, you know, the average,
but it's really not
a good one, even though
we still use a lot
of the the numbers that
are coming from it.
But I want everybody
to understand that this
is just a very, very
imaginary construct.
Obviously, our body
weights not only are in
totality are different,
but they're very much
dependent on age,
they're dependent on
adiposity, and I've kind
of included that here.
The national average
of our weight has been
increased by 20-some-odd
pounds in the last 35 years.
So we've all become a
lot fatter, and that
actually can make
a difference in the
total amounts of the
volumes we're talking
about. But generally,
ballpark figures,
the breakdown is here,
that we can, you know,
if you break apart the
total amount of water
we have in our body,
the total body water,
you know, in this imaginary
172 kilogram person,
comes out around 345 liters
total body water. of that,
40% of it is inside the
cells, intercellular fluid,
and the rest of it is
found in the interstitium,
in transcellular compartments,
and in our plasma.
I want to break down
the volumes. Those were
just percentages. This
is sort of what they fall
into, and you may remember
my comment in a lecture
last year, know your
electrolytes, and this
slide gives us a
breakdown of the
general major
electrolytes and players
and other variables that
are important in body
fluid regulation. So we
make the distinction here,
plasma membrane, and
I'm going to make that
distinction over and over
again, so pay attention,
versus a capillary
barrier, versus a
epithelial cell
barrier. There are
differences, and
I'll touch on them.
As you can see, there is
very little differences
in electrolytes across
capillary barriers. There
are some, but not really,
really dramatic. Huge
electrolyte differences when
you compare intracellular
fluids to interstitial
fluid and to plasma.
And transcellular fluid,
you can think of it as the
liquids that are found in
specific anatomical areas.
For example, the blood
-brain barrier separates the
central nervous system,
and the fluid within that,
the cerebrospinal fluid,
is a transcellular fluid.
Fluids in our GI system
would be considered that,
storage of bile salts
in the gallbladder, it's
obviously it's in a fluid
milieu, so those are all
transcellular fluids, and the
regulation is really based
dependent on the cells
surrounding those barriers.
I may have shared this last
year, but if not,
it's here now.
If you took solute transport,
and this is basically a
summary slide from last
year's lectures, movement
through plasma membranes of
everything except for water.
You can see that it
breaks down into passive
versus carrier mediated.
If you Remember,
passive movement is really
based on movement of
compounds based on their
concentration gradient.
Carrier-mediated, it's
always movement of compounds
against a concentration.
And they can either be
direct active transport
by expending energy, like
any kind of a pump or an
ATPase. One molecule of ATP
is used to move one
molecule of X against its
concentration gradient.
That's a primary active
transporter. Secondary active
transporters will depend
on the activity of these
primary active transporters
for the movements. And
we'll touch on these kind
of definitions repeatedly
in not only this lecture,
but the upcoming lectures
on renal physiology.
So let's start off
by talking about the
movements of water and
water homeostasis. Again,
we talked about solutes,
so this is water.
So obviously, normal cell
function requires a very
tightly regulated intracellular
milieu and the regulation
of the concentration because
small changes in concentration
can have really dramatic
effects on the various
processes that are
happening within the cell.
And this term homeostasis,
the maintenance of volume
and composition of body
fluids, is accomplished by
transport of substances and
water in and out of the cell.
In a healthy person, this
happens without any significant
changes in the volume or
composition of the body
fluid compartments, you
know, on a day-to-day basis.
So we have various
numbers of systems to,
you know, designed to achieve
homeostasis. Up here
and in this inset, I've
set up what happens,
for example,
when, you know, when we
have changes in water,
either water deficit,
when you're really, really
thirsty or water excess when
you drank a lot of fluid.
Open, you know, the
human body is considered
an open system and,
you know, anything
we gain we lose every
time that we mismanage
this balance is
when we have issues.
So maintenance of steady
-state balance is integral
to our health and almost
everything in our for
maintaining a steady state
requires a set point.
Think about it in terms of
a thermostat. You design,
you know, you go home and
you set up your thermostats
for 74 degrees and 74 degrees
if it goes too much then
nothing will kick in, but
if it's below 74 then the
heat turns on and temperature
will go up. So the effector
signals must be, so whatever
sets it up must be able
to generate an effector
signal that can lead to
changes. And of course, you
must have something to respond,
so you need a, you know,
you need to have a furnace
in order to heat up your
house. So, you know, having
a thermostat without a heat
source is pointless, you
know, setting up a thermostat
if you don't have an air
conditioner to cool your
house doesn't do anything. And
of course, it must be sensitive
enough for the changes.
You don't want something
to only get activated when
you're 20 degrees above
the temperature you've set.
So water can move through
intercellular and extracellular
compartments across the
plasma membrane. We'll
talk a little bit about
that. And water moves between
the vascular and interstitial
compartments across capillary
walls. But the pathways
and the driving forces for
these water movements are
different. and the schematic
on the lower right-hand
side kind of gives you,
gives you an idea. So water
is going between interstitial
fluid and extracellular
fluid, and at the same time
water is going back and
forth between intracellular
fluid and extracellular
fluid, but what controls them
are different, and what can
control them is different.
And going back to the
top in this case, and
it's something that
we'll go back to, what
happens if you're, you
know, when you have
an H, when you have a
water deficit? Well,
the set point, then your
concentration of water
is going to be lower, and
that's going to activate
the thirst response, and
that thirst response,
A, you're thirsty, you
feel thirsty, and B, you'll
stimulate the secretion
of ADH, AVP, and that'll
influence water input.
And then vice versa,
if you have too much
water, let's say you
drank a lot of, a lot
of, you know, water,
and there you can
have the set point is
going to be altered.
It's going to be
too low. So then you
get a withdrawal
of this ADH-AVP and
that's going to
stimulate water output.
And then water is
lost through variable,
various, excuse me, various.
So water movement across
biological membrane
is always passive. What
does that mean? There
is no pump. There is no
active transport that
regulates water movement.
Water movement is
always driven by its
concentration gradient.
Now, in a artificial setting,
we can, you know, we can
see the water can move through
a lipid bilayer, except
that it's really, really
low and it's a finite rate,
so it takes forever to
equilibrate concentrations.
Slow diffusion can also
depend on the lipid
composition of the
cells in that tissue.
All lipid bilayers are
not created equally,
even though we draw them
as such. I mean, this
is one of the times
that, you know, things
like this end up being,
you know, promoting a
false impression that
they have, there is a
polarity and the various
different types of
lipids can go to change
into different organs.
Obviously, let's say your
neurons will have different
plasma membrane components
than cardiac myocytes.
Regardless of that, the
movement of water across
cell membranes occurs
through a transmembrane pore,
collectively called
aquaporins. These are passive
conduits for water. It's a
large family of intrinsic
membrane proteins, so they
require insertion into the
lipid bilayer, obviously,
to give it a, to, for,
for its function. And they
facilitate the rapid transport
of water across cell
membranes. They basically
are opening up a pore into,
into the cell membrane.
The table on the right
gives you the number of, you
know, the isoforms in this
big superfamily. There
are 13 components of it.
I don't expect anybody to
memorize the ones. You will
refer to a couple of them.
For example, we'll come
back later on to aquaporin
2 in our collecting ducts.
But you can see, like
in terms of the kidney,
aquaporin 1, aquaporin 3,
4, 6, 7, 8, you know,
they're all fairly
represented, 11 are
well represented in the
kidney. But really, the
most important one that
we'll talk about
eventually is aquaporin 2.
Water is not the
only thing that
they can serve
as a conduit for.
They can actually also be
permeable to glycerol. Glycerol
is important for formation
of triglycerides and
phospholipidins, so it's a
substrate for further work.
So the driving force,
obviously, as I said,
it's a concentration of
water, and reevaluate
that using the osmotic
pressure difference.
And osmotic pressure,
it's indicated by pi, and
that's what I'll refer
to back and forth. The
osmotic pressure pi of
intercellular fluid and
extracellular fluid is
determined by ions and by
molecules, macromolecules,
like glucose and proteins.
We call it osmotic
pressure, but it's not
a pressure in the
sense of a hydrostatic
pressure. When we
say osmotic pressure
difference, we really
just mean osmolality.
It's just osmolality
expressed in pressure units.
And you've seen
this number before,
the osmolality of
intracellular and
extracellular fluid
is around between 280
-295 milliosmoles per
kilogram of water.
And when these values
are the same across a
plasma membrane, the cell
volume remains constant.
So in almost all cases,
osmolarity inside
the cell is equal to
osmolarity outside the
cell. right? If there was
a delta, if there
was a difference in
osmolality, cells would
either shrink or swell.
So how is it related to
osmolality? You know, I
always tell everybody, if
you can hear me say, if
you've spoken to me, that
I don't want to give you
a lot of equations. I
don't expect anybody to
memorize equations or
apply the equations to any
questions. But the point that I
bring this up is
the osmolarity is
proportional, directly
proportional to pressure
differences. And you can
measure the, you can calculate
the pressure using Vanhoef
equation. The variables
will be the gas constant
of the compound, the
absolute temperature, and
obviously the osmolality.
Here I am just telling
you that if one change of
one milliosmol equals
to a change of about 20
millimeters of mercury at 37
degrees body temperature so
small amounts of osmolarity
can lead to significant
changes in pressure 20
millimeters of mercury is
really a huge pressure
difference you can feel it
if somebody pressed
against your skin.
And remember, water will
move by osmosis toward the
solution with the higher
osmolality. So the higher
the osmolality, you want
to think of it as the
lower the concentration of
water. And everything goes
toward the higher
concentration, you know, toward.
So a higher concentration
always pushes
a movement in solutes. In
this case, higher osmolality
will pull water across a
plasma membrane. So, and
this movement by osmotic
gradient is obviously
called osmosis. It is not
the only driving force. There
is another driving force,
and that is the hydrostatic
pressure. That's a real
pressure, and it's, the
movement is dependent, the
water movement of water
is dependent on both.
However, animal cells are not
rigid. We don't have a cell
wall and we don't really
tolerate any significant
changes in hydrostatic
pressure without something
bad happening, without
deformation. So, for example,
in this case I have here,
osmolality outside is 290
milliosmoles, osmolality
inside is 295 milliosmoles.
there is no difference
in hydrostatic pressure.
So despite that, you
have movement of water
going into the cell because
water will go toward higher
osmolality. Osmolality
is going to be pulling
water. Water concentration
here is higher compared
to water concentration
here, and concentrations
go from high to low.
But in the end,
except when we're
talking about
osmolality of water,
right? Osmols of water.
So this hydrostatic
pressure is not
a significant driving
force for water
transport across
a plasma membrane.
So that's really that
portion. So a summary so far.
I just want us to reiterate
pathways and driving
forces for water and
solutes are different across
cell membranes and across
barriers. We did a lot
of solute transport
across cell membranes last
year. This was water movement
across cell membranes.
Diffusion through the
lipid bilayer depends
on lipid composition
and movement of water
occurs through aquaporins,
and hydrostatic
pressure is not a
significant driving force,
but inter-rosmotic pressure is.
So let's go back to the
anatomy of our body fluids.
And now we start talking about
capillary barriers and
the movement across
biological barriers that
are not plasma membranes.
So we will talk a
little bit about
epithelial cells and
capillary barriers
and what roles they play in the
control of water and
solute movements.
So how do the different
gradients of all the
substances in the
interstitium and intercellular
milieu contribute to the
movement of water? So
one thing we have to
kind of always remember
is that the product of
the diffusible ions on one
side will be equal
to the product of the
diffusible ions on the
other side of the membrane.
There
is an electrochemical
gradient produced
by unequal distribution.
And unequal
distribution of charged
particles is what
creates our transmembrane
potential differences,
also known as the
membrane potential, that
we can calculate using
the Nernst equation.
And sodium chloride is
largely excluded from the
intercellular component
of our body by the
activity of the sodium
-potassium ATBs. And you can
see that here. So we
have the plasma membrane.
Sodium is 142 millimolars.
Chloride is 102. The
other sodiums that
don't match with
chloride usually
are bound to other
anions like citrate
or any other kind of
negative monovalent ion in
the solution. While sodium
in intracellular fluid
is 15, chloride is almost
the same. There's a
big difference in potassium,
right? Potassium is
low outside, high inside,
and that's all virtue
of the activity of the
sodium-potassium ATPase.
Why does, you know,
and it's really, really
important. How is it
important? Well, if there's
an absence of sodium
potassium ATPase, cells
will swell and burst,
even if the concentration,
the osmolalities are
equal inside and outside.
But that's because
we're not taking
into consideration
other molecules.
specifically impermeable
molecules, which in this case,
we are really are talking
about cytosolic proteins.
Cytosolic proteins are
mostly negatively charged.
And this difference in
the protein amounts in
intracellular versus
interstitial is what ends
up giving us another
player in our diffusion
gradient. And this osmotic
diffusion gradient,
created by negatively charged
impermeable molecules,
is what attract water
into that compartment.
The mechanism that does
that is described in
what's called the Gibbs
-Dunnan Equilibrium. And the
Gibbs-Dunnan Equilibrium
guides the behavior of
charged particle near a
semi-permeable membrane.
The next slides will go
into a little bit detail
about that. So the Gibbs
-Dunnan Equilibrium, again, how
cells and blood vessels
manage electric charge, ion
concentrations, and fluid
movements. Named after an
American engineer and an
English chemist, this was
the chemist was, they
were working together on a
university project and their
collaborations expanded from
outside of their realms of
their interests. One of the
more fascinating stories,
if you're curious about it.
So one of the things
it's given, most
proteins are negatively
charged in a physiological
environment. A lot
of our proteins have
higher proportion of
acidic amino acids,
glutamic acid aspartate,
and and a phosphate
additions to proteins,
not only in a
signaling moiety, but
also just natively bound.
So if we have a semi
-permeable barrier,
and we have, we, we
add, you know, we, our
extracellular fluid is
equimolar sodium and chloride,
while our intracellular
fluid is, is sodium without
any chloride and protein
content, indicated
here as X. I put X150 to
indicate this is negative
150 charges, right? 150
milliequivalents for the
one millimolar of proteins
that we have. have.
So if the membrane is
permeable to sodium chloride
and water, but it's
impermeable to X, what happens?
So A,
chloride will move
down its concentration
gradient, right? There is
a, you know, 150 to zero,
so chloride will move
down, but it will not
equilibrate because
eventually, as chloride moves
in, sodium will move
in to be equal voltage,
and sodium concentration
will go up, chloride
will go up also, but
not to the equilibration
until there is a
transmembrane difference.
So as sodium enters the cell,
sodium intercellular increases,
sodium exocellular decreases,
and this will create an inside
negative membrane voltage.
And this is a good
thing. You attract
sodium, creates a
membrane voltage,
a membrane potential.
we've talked about.
So we said this, sodium goes
up, chloride will go up,
sodium outside will go
down, chloride outside will
go down, right? So let's
say 10 millimolar shift.
However, it's still
not in equilibrium.
This is just an
intermediate step, because
if you cross multiply an
equation, and I'm not going
to do that, we find that
the product are not equal.
So the constraint of the
system is the total number
of charges. So they must be
equal. They must equilibrium,
total number of positive
charges must equal the
total number of negative
charges in each compartment.
So we need this to
move until sodium and
chloride are equal. And
then the final ratio
corresponds to the nurse
potential of both ions.
So in the final equilibrium,
sodium and chloride
will be distributed
so the concentration
is balanced. And
this balance is called
the Donnan ratio.
So when the ratios of
positive and negative
ions are balanced, are
in equilibrium. It's
called the Donnan
ratio. They're in
equilibrium, but more
asthmatic active, you know,
particles are on the
inside than on the outside,
right? So you still
have more, you know, in
this case, you'll have
280, right? Versus 170
millimolar comparison.
Water can't be in an
equilibrium, right, because
these are concentrations.
So water will move
into the cell to change
the concentration. And
very little water
needs to go into the
cell to generate a
hydrostatic pressure,
to generate hydrostatic
pressure to oppose the
additional entry of water.
And this equilibrium
hydrostatic pressure
opposes the osmotic pressure
difference, right? So the
delta mu, the hydrostatic
pressure, is opposite
the osmotic pressure. And
equilibrium means that the
differences are the same.
But if water is
moving in, and very
little can cause a
change in pressure,
then the distribution
of ions toward
the Donnan ratio
can lead to water
entry and cell
swelling and bursting.
Does this happen?
No, because the Donnan
equilibrium ignores
all the other ions,
other than sodium,
chloride, and the proteins
that are negative.
It's just an important
reminder that the negative
charge on impermeant
solutes lead to bursting,
and cells have to work in
order to counteract this
passive swelling. This is
osmotic work, and we need
osmotic work to exclude
sodium chloride from the
cell and to make the cell
functionally impermeable to
sodium chloride. Again,
functionally impermeable.
So, and this is a steady
state maintained by
active transport, and
it's maintained by
our old friend, the
sodium-potassium ATPase.
sodium-potassium ATPase
will pump sodium out,
bring sodium in, excuse me,
potassium in, and maintain
a balance of water and
chloride in order to maintain
the volume now we can block
this and in fact it's it's
something that happens
not only in nature but in
drug therapy digitalis
glycosides are a class of drugs
you learn about them later
on that are derived from the
digitalis purpurea gland
plant foxglove it it has a
alkaloid that can block the
activity of
digitalis glycosides.
And once you block the sodium
potassium ATPase, water
will go in, the cells will
expand and burst. And why
would a plant do that? Well,
why do plants create any
alkaloids, right? They do
that as toxins to prevent
themselves from being
eaten. So it's a defense
mechanism that humans
have used for drug
therapy, like everything
else that we use from
extracting from nature
for our therapeutic needs.
So the response to cell
swelling is if you have
a decrease in extracellular
fluid osmolality.
This attracts water
into the cell. The cells
respond by activating
solute efflux, and this
is called the regulatory
volume decrease,
right? And this
exact opposite things
happen in a response
to cell shrinkage.
You have an increase in
extracellular of fluid
osmolality. This sucks water
out of the cell, so the
cells will respond by
activating solute uptake,
right? And this is known
as regulatory volume
increase. All of it is
constant work to maintain the
Donnan equilibrium. But
you'll never, you know,
again, the cells are
always doing it. You never
reach it. It's always an
attempt to get that far.
So, before we talk about
barriers, let's have a
couple of slides talking
about the microcirculation.
And because, again, the
movement across cellular
barriers really falls
down to a lot about the
movement across in the
microcirculation. You'll be
doing the cardiovascular
system soon, but remember
the primary function of
the cardiovascular system
is to maintain a suitable
environment for survival
and function, and that
does so by nutrient
exchange, and the microcirculation
is, you know, it's
considered to be the
business end of our system.
So in generalities, if they are
capillaries are the
primary site of gas,
nutrient, water, and waste
product exchange, and
these are the blood
vessels that go from the
first order arterioles
to first order venules.
So they're not arterioles
and they're not
venules. They come off
of them. In most, but
not all, that flow
through microcirculation
is there to serve our
nutritional needs.
However, in some
tissues, that's
not the case. For example,
in the kidney, one example,
and the skin is another one.
One of the interesting
things across these
capillaries, you
have right at the
junction of the arterioles
to the capillaries.
You can have pre
-capillary sphincters.
These pre-capillary
sphincters are
found at the transition
of capillaries
and some arterioles.
Again, not all.
They're smooth muscle cells,
vascular smooth muscle
cells. They're not innervated,
so there's no ganglia
associated with it that
controls contraction. They are
very responsive to paracrine
and autocrine influences.
So the tissues and the
cells surrounding them
probably control its
relaxation and constriction
to a large degree. And
you can see that can
really make sense, right?
If you don't have a
lot of glucose, you have
too much, let's say,
metabolites, of, you know,
anaerobic or aerobic
metabolism that
can act as a stimulus
for dilation to
increase the flow to
bring back nutrients.
So,
they become integral to
modulating exchange within
the capillaries because they
can affect concentrations
and different variables.
The endothelial cells
in capillaries are linked
together in varying degrees
via tight junctions,
adhering junctions, and intra
-endothelial junctions. And
these are proteins such
as the clodins as well as
occludins that can fit,
that basically stick
the side of the endothelial
cells to make sure that
nothing can go through
the gaps in these cells.
In broad definition, there
are some differences.
Epithelium is an
uninterrupted sheet of
cells that are joined
together by complexes.
Vascular endothelium
is a subset of
epithelium. They're
highly specialized,
specific type of
epithelial tissues.
And this table here
gives you the difference
between the histological
differences,
cell types. You can
see some, you know, the
epithelium, you have
various different
morphologies, while
endothelium is only one.
Where they are, you know,
endothelium is really
the internal surfaces
of the cardiovascular
and lymphatic
systems, and they
constitute the capillaries.
Epithelial cells,
a lot of them have
papillary projections,
brush borders,
while endothelial
cells are smooth.
Epithelial cells
have a distinct
polarity. They have poles,
basolateral and apical poles,
while endothelial doesn't.
Different types of secretion.
The majority of the
secretions of epithelial
cells is mucus, complex
carbohydrates along with
water, and prostaglandin E2,
one of the species of
prostaglandins that are
derived from arachidonic
acid. And they rapidly
regenerate. They have a
high regeneration capacity.
Endothelial cells don't.
They have very limited
regenerative capacity. When you
damage endothelial cells,
it's pretty bad. You have
long-term damage. They're
considered to be simple squamous
cells, and they secrete a
lot more interesting and
biologically diverse secretions,
such as nitric oxide,
PGI-2, also called
clostacyclin,
and various growth
factors and vasoactive
factors. And you
can see here, again,
a comparison between an
arterial precapillary
sphincter and a true
capillary. You can see that
the ratio of endothelial
cells to vascular smooth
muscle is dramatic. There
is no smooth muscle in
capillaries. It's really
all endothelial cells.
They really just are
just a single continuous
layer of endothelial
cells. They have a basement
membrane and interspersed
cells called pericytes.
Pericytes are also
called mural cells. They
have contractile ability,
but they're not smooth
muscle cells. So they may
act like smooth muscle
cells, but they're not
smooth muscle cells. And
they're essential for
regulation of blood flow.
We can categorize
capillaries into three
distinctions based on
their degree of leakiness,
if you want to use
regular vernacular.
Most of our capillaries
are continuous capillaries.
This is a good example
of it right over here.
They have tight
junctions, adhering
junctions, and a
great example of it
is most of the
blood-brain barrier.
You also have
fenestrated capillaries.
In this case, the
endothelial cells are
thin and perforated
with fenestrations.
Fenestration is another
word for window. Fenestra
is Latin for window. If
any of you ever go to
Europe, please go to
Prague and go to where the
first and second defenestrations
of Prague happened.
It's one of my favorite
historical occurrences.
And these fenestrated
capillaries often
surround epithelia such
as small intestine,
glands, and the kidney.
And then finally you have
discontinuous sinusoidal
capillaries. So they have
large gaps and very large
windows, large fenestrae. And
it's close contact between
body and tissue and exchange
of materials. So places
like the liver, where you
have exchange of proteins
and lipoproteins, or spleen,
where you have exchange
of cells is where you have
discontinuous sinusoidal
capillaries. Here's
another slide, shows them
bigger. This is a nice
electron microscope, shows you
the cell body of the pericyte
and how it sends out these
projections and it can cause
contraction, constriction
of capillaries just by
the action of one cell.
Here is a fenestrated
capillary versus
a sinusoidal. You
can see the degree
of the holes that
are different.
If you are from Wisconsin
or you like cheese,
this is a baby Swiss, while
this is regular Swiss.
I do not know how they
taste. I know how baby
Swiss and Swiss cheese
taste, but yeah, I don't know
if the capillaries have
a taste difference, but
that's neither here or
there or important at all.
So how is water exchange across
capillary walls generated?
So interstitial fluid
surrounds and bathes all the
cells of our body that are
non-blood, right? Obviously
blood is in the vasculature
and is surrounded by blood,
not by interstitial fluid.
And capillary walls separate
the intravascular and
interstitial compartments.
And in some tissues,
this is not,
is a non-nutritional exchange.
So what can guide, regulate
this exchange? Well,
the first one
we'll talk about is
hydrostatic pressure.
And this includes all
the sources of
intravascular pressure.
So not only the, not
only the pressure that we
get from gravity, right?
So hydrostatic pressure
when you're standing
up is higher in your
lower extremities than
they are in your upper
extremities, but not
when you're lying down.
And in this case, if you're
going to make a schematic,
you can draw hydrostatic
pressure inside the
capillary versus hydrostatic
pressure in the interstitium.
And this is always
higher. And this will push
water from the capillary
into the interstitium.
So it's a very important
force for driving fluid
across cell barriers. Also
small solutes. Electrolytes
permeate freely across
most cell barriers and
the borough along with the
water. But the pressure
difference is much, much
higher than any kind
of an oncotic influence
on these small solutes. So
they do not exert a driving
force for water movement
across cell barriers.
So the only net osmotic
force that acts across
capillary walls can be caused
by asymmetric distribution
of plasma proteins.
That can cause differences
in these two variables,
but not in the plasma
hydrostatic variables.
So proteins make a
big difference in the
cellular barriers.
If you remember that
they can be zero because
the barrier will not allow
proteins to cross. And we
really are talking about
proteins, we're talking
about albumin. Albumin is the
lion's share of plasma
proteins, about 54%. And here's
a sample of blood. If you
take a little, you know,
if you spin it down, you
can see the red blood cells,
white blood cells, platelets in
the buffy coat and the plasma,
nice and clear and a
healthy person, yellowish,
the majority of it
is albumin. You can
visualize it very
nicely and it's because
albumin binds a lot of
compounds so you have a
variable molecular
weight and differences in
charge, depending on
what is bound to it. And
this can be observed
if you run a two
-dimensional gel based on
molecular weight and pH,
just a drop of human plasma,
you can see the majority
of what you find is in
the albumin compartment.
Other parts are
immunoglobulins,
you know, especially IgG.
And so IgG, you know,
immunoglobulins, the
various different ones will
break up, you know,
about 38% of the plasma
proteins and the rest of
them are broken down to
fibrinogen and miscellaneous
enzymes and hormones.
But protein
concentrations are
higher in plasma than
they are in interstitial,
right, unless
the proteins can get across
the capillary barrier.
If they can't get across
the capillary barrier,
then we have set up
a gradient. And this
gradient pulls the fluid
back into the capillary.
And this is called the
colloid osmotic pressure,
also known as the oncotic
pressure. Delta mu,
you know, onc, I'll
indicate it. So for when it
comes to protein, we
refer to it as oncotic,
because that's where you
can have a concentration
difference across the
capillary barrier. You don't
have electrolytes.
Electrolytes will go through
those capillary fenestrae
without any problem.
The concept of ultrafiltration
occurs when you
have higher hydrostatic
pressure than oncotic pressure,
and you push the water
out of the capillary.
but vice versa can also
be true. If you have more
plasma proteins in the
intravascular compartment
than in the
interstitial, you can
pull it back into
the capillary.
And water is at equilibrium
when the colloid
and osmotic hydrostatic
pressures are equal.
So the regular relationship
between these two and
the roles in regulating
fluid exchange was was
explored and characterized
by Henry Starling and this
is also known as Starling's
hypothesis where he
calculated the rate of fluid
movement based on three
or if you want to call it
five different variables.
The variables are capillary
hydrostatic pressure,
interstitial
oncotic pressure,
plasma versus interstitial,
and the filtration coefficient.
So what is the filtration
coefficient? Well,
it's a quantitative
assessment of the capillary
wall permeability and
the total surface area.
So KFs are different in
different tissues, and they
are variables. And you can
see the total surface area
and the permeability can
change not only by actions
of the sphincters, but
by actions of other cells
that are associated with
the capillary barrier, such
as pericytes, as I mentioned
before, and mesangial
cells, which we'll talk
about in the next lectures.
Further solute exchange
across cellular barriers
can occur either paracellularly
or transcellularly.
So this is for anything
that is lipid-insoluble,
so not lipids, not
gas, usually proteins.
Endothelial cells deposit
a layer of glycocalyx
in their basement
membrane. And these
are macromolecules
with negative charges.
And they'll repel other
macromolecules with negative
charges and favor molecules
with positive charges.
And so they can
cross the barrier
based on that paracellularly.
Transcellular is more
of an active process.
Not really for
neutral molecules.
It's mostly for
different size molecules.
So you can have, and
in some cases, water.
you can have
translocation of the
compound across a
cellular barrier,
not around it. And it
requires endocytosis, movement
through the cell, and
then exocytosis. So
endocytosis can either
occur by nonspecific uptake.
It can happen by
internalization, by pinching off
large particles,
macrophages are
famous for their
phagocytic activities,
and receptor-mediated
endocytosis, where based
on a binding by specific
molecules to their
specific cell receptors,
they are removed. You
can see this in a lot
of degradative pathways.
Yeah, and the paracellular
pathways are for
solutes that are smaller
than albumin that can
cross, that must traverse
the wall by diffusion.
One of the results of these
movements is the creation
of an electrochemical
gradient across epithelial
barriers. This is not a
plasma membrane. This is
epithelial barriers, one
side of a luminal barrier to
another, right? So if this
is in the lumen, you can
have a difference in charge
compared to interstitium.
Again, not plasma membrane,
so let's be careful
about that. This is
called the transepithelial
voltage, VTE, and it's
the difference in the
potential energy in
between either sides of a
barrier. And they can have
high or low electrical
resistance based on
their tight junctions.
The tighter, the more
junctions they have,
the higher the
electrical resistance,
the lower, the leakier
they are, the lower
the electrical resistance.
And in general,
leaky epithelia perform bulk
transepithelial transport,
while tight epithelia
generate transepithelial
concentration and osmotic
gradients. And we'll see
that dramatically when we
talk about our nephrons.
And we'll finish off
by talking about the
effects of salinity on
body fluid compartments.
And how, if we, and
how do these fluids
change in response
to different stimuli?
So adding different
combinations of water and
solute-free water to
the extracellular fluid
will alter the volume and
composition of all the
body fluid compartments.
And these effects are
really seen when we give
intravenous therapy.
So let's talk about
normal. Normal we
have here, total
body water, right?
based on the numbers we
had before. If I give
somebody an infusion of
1.5 liters of isotonic
saline, the effect
of osmolality doesn't
change, right? The saline,
the concentration is
the same as interstitial
exocellular fluid.
All I'll do is add 18, you
know, 1.5 liters to the
exocellular fluid volume,
and you don't have any
changes in osmotic gradient
across the membrane,
right? And these numbers,
especially when it
comes to looking at these
movements, are based on
the blood body fluids of
a 70 kilogram per person.
Just know the
generalities, that there is
movement if you give an
isotonic solution just
into the extracellular
fluid compartment.
That is the plasma and
interstitial fluid.
and there is no movement
in or out of intercellular
fluid. How about the
opposite one? What if I give
you 1.5 liters of solute
-free water? Well, nobody
will do that. Infusion water
is bad, right? But we do
that similarly when we
give isotonic glucose,
dextrose solutions. The dextrose
will will get metabolized
very quickly to carbon
dioxide and water. And
remember, carbon dioxide
gases are not solutes. So
there's no solutes left
behind in the exocellular
fluid. So what happens then?
Well, then initially, the
fluid volume will go into
the exocellular fluid,
and then decreasing its
osmolality, right? Because
you're only adding water
for all practical purposes.
Then this draws in
water. So you get a loss
of water into the
interstitial, into
intercellular fluid
until they equilibrate.
So adding 1.5 liters of
isotonic glucose is similar
to adding 1.5 liters of
water-free, except we
don't do that because if
you add solute-free water
at any site, you cause
massive tissue damage,
right, to the site of
injection because you'll
just burst the cells. The
cells will just explode.
How about the opposite of
that addition of pure and
ACL. And this is not really
infusion of a sodium chloride
solution. We can just
usually see that in ingestion
of sodium chloride. And
let's do potato chips. I
did the calculation. 13.5
grams of sodium chloride is,
you know, and is kind of
like a little bit less than
the amount we would get in
a bag of potato chips. So
a lot of potato, a lot of
salt when we do our potato
chips snacking. So what
happens then? Well, then the
sodium chloride is all in
the extracellular fluid,
right? Then the osmolality
will go up. What happens
then? Well, then we start
getting fluid water movement
going from the intercellular
space to the extracellular
space until the osmolalities
equilibrate, which are
still probably a little
bit higher, but that's a
cellular response before we
have a total body response.
So as a final note, interstitium
was always considered
to be an artificial space,
something that we use
in our discussions, but
there's more and more people
who actually think that
this is a real space and
it's unrecognized and
therefore can be manipulated.
If so, I think it's
really interesting.
If you're interested in it,
Neil D. Thies, he's an
NYU pathologist. They've
done some really
interesting histology on it.
Anyway,
now that's this
lecture. Thank you very
much, and here is
the lecture feedback
form, and wait until
our next lecture.